Library of Social and Economic Aspects of Medicine of Michael M. Davis,
Library of Social and Economic Aspects of Medicine of Michael M. Davis
- Medical Care in the United States, Series 2
  - Group Practice
    - Group Practice Plans: A Listing by State (Issued by H.E.W., Division of Program Research) (Box 23)
    - Hospital Discrimination against Group Practice (Box 23)
    - Preliminary Directory of Medical Groups in the U.S., 1959 (Box 23)
    - Pamphlets (Box 23)
    - Specific Group Practice Organizations (Box 24)
    - Statistics (Box 24)
  - Specific Union Prepayment Plans
    - Union Health Centers - Directory (Box 24)
    - A.F.L. Medical Service Plan (Box 24)
    - Allentown, PA: Local 119, Health Fund of Male Apparel Industry (Box 24)
    - Amalgamated Clothing Workers (Box 24)
    - City of Hope Medical Center (Box 24)
    - ILGWU (Box 24)
    - ILWU-PMA Welfare Fund (Int. Longshoremen's and Warehouse Union - Pacific Maritime Association) (Box 24)
    - St. Louis Labor Health Institute (Box 24)
    - UAW-CIO Health Institute (Box 24)
    - UAW-CIO Collective Bargaining (Box 24)
    - UAW - Community Health Association, Detroit (Box 24)
    - United Electrical Workers (Box 24)
    - United Mine Workers (Box 24-25)
    - United Steel Workers (Box 25)
    - Various Health Plans (Box 25)
  - Medical Education
    - Articles and Clippings - General (Box 25)
    - Federal Aid to Medical Education (Box 25)
    - Medical Advice (publication) (Box 25)
    - Medical Education in Hospitals (Box 25)
    - Intern Training (Box 25)
    - Public Health Training (Box 25)
    - Ration of Applicants to Population, 1952-1953 (Box 25)
    - Regional Cooperation (Box 25)
    - Reports re: Medical Education (Box 25)
    - Social and Economic Aspects of Medicine - Teaching (Box 25)
    - Sociological Studies (Box 26)
    - Surgeon General's Report on Financing of Medical Schools, 1950 (Box 26)
    - Various Reports and Pamphlets (Box 26)
  - Medical Personnel
    - Reports - General (Box 26)
    - Health Manpower (see also Public Health, Personal) (Box 26)
  - Physicians
    - Administration as a Career (Box 26)
    - Attitudes of Individual Physicians toward N.H.I. (Box 26)
    - Choice and Change of Doctors (Box 26)
    - Depression (Box 26)
    - Discrimination in Medicine (Box 26)
    - Distribution and Supply of Physicians (Box 26)
    - Distribution of Medical College Graduates (Box 26)
    - Draft (Box 26)
    - Druggists - Tie-in (Box 26)
    - Ethics (Box 26)
    - Family Physician (Box 27)
    - Fees (Box 27)
    - Fee Schedules - Sliding Scale (Box 27)
    - Fee Splitting (Box 27)
    - Foreign Physicians - Problem (Box 27)
    - Free Services Given (Box 27)
    - General Practitioner (see also Family Physician) (Box 27)
    - Government Service - Physicians In (Box 27)
    - Hospitals (Box 27)
    - Income (Box 27)
    - Kick-backs (Box 27)
    - Labor and Physicians (Box 27)
    - Malpractice Suits and Medical Professional Liability (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27)
    - Mortality (Box 27)
    - Negroes (Box 27)
    - Patient Load (Box 27)
    - Patient Relations (Box 27)
    - Payment by Capitation (Box 27)
    - Politics (not A.M.A.) - Physicians In (Box 27)
    - Public Health Programs (Box 27)
    - Public Opinion about Doctors (Box 27)
    - "Quackery" (Box 27)
    - Reider Interviews (Box 27)
    - Rural Areas (Box 27)
    - Salaried (Box 27)
    - Services Rendered (Box 27)
    - Shortage (Box 27)
    - Social Security (Box 27)
    - Specialists and General Practitioners (Box 27)
    - Taft - Physicians for (Box 27)
    - War - Shortage of Doctors (Box 27)
    - Women - Physicians (Box 27)
  - Specialists
    - General (Box 28)
    - Consultation (Box 28)
    - Anesthesiology (Box 28)
    - Pathology (Box 28)
    - Radiology (Box 28)
    - Surgeons (Box 28)
    - Obstetrics and Gynecology (Box 28)
    - Ophthalmology (Box 28)
    - Pediatrics (Box 28)
    - Psychiatry (Box 28)
    - Internists (Box 28)
  - Dentists
    - Dentistry - General (Box 28)
    - Dentistry and N.H.I. (Box 28)
    - Dental Care - History (Box 28)
    - Dental Care Received (Box 28)
    - Cost of Dental Care (Box 28)
    - Dental Education (Box 28)
    - Distribution and Supply of Dentists (Box 28)
    - Flouridation (Box 28)
    - Income - Dentists (Box 28)
    - Dental Group Practice (Box 28)
    - Prepayment Plans - Dentists In (Box 28)
    - Public Health and Dental Care (Box 28)
    - Organizations (Box 28)
    - Pamphlets (1940-1949 and Current) (Box 28)
  - Medical Social Workers
    - Articles, Reports, and Pamphlets (Box 29)
  - Home Makers
    - Home Makers (Box 29)
  - Paramedical Personnel
    - Paramedical Personnel (Box 29)
  - Nurses
    - Nurses and N.H.I. (Box 29)
    - Nursing - General (Box 29)
    - Nursing Care Received (Box 29)
    - Nursing Education (Box 29)
    - Graduate Nurses (Box 29)
    - Home Nursing (Box 29)
    - Practical Nurses (Box 29)
    - Prepayment Plans - Nurses In (Box 29)
    - Public Health Nurses (Box 29)
    - Nursepower and Mobilization (Box 29)
    - Shortage of Nurses (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous Pamphlets (Box 29)
    - Organizations - Nurses (Box 30)
  - Optometry - Optometrists
    - General (Box 30)
    - American Optometric Association - current File, Dr. Felix Koetting (Box 30)
    - A.O.A. - Optometric Literature (Box 30)
    - MMD Speech at St. Louis, Mo., 10/25/58 (Box 30)
    - A.O.A. - Current File of Correspondence with Sharman, Vision Service Plans, etc. (Box 30)
    - A.O.A. and Prepaid Health Plans (Box 30)
    - A.O.A. and World War II (Box 30)
    - A.O.A. - Correspondence and Material Prior to 1950 (Box 30)
    - A.O.A. - "Public Health Optometry,", 1939 (Box 30)
  - Pharmacy - Druggists
    - Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Data (Box 30)
    - Public Attitude Towards Prescription Costs (Box 30)
    - Formularies in Hospitals (Box 30)
  - Osteopaths
    - Osteopaths (Box 30)
  - Chiropractors and Others
    - Chiropractors and Others (Box 30)
  - Reed Articles
    - "The Healing Cults"; "Midwives, Chiropodists, and Optometrists" (Box 30)
  - Hospitals
    - Bibliography (Box 30)
    - Hospitals and N.H.I. (K.G. Clark) (Box 30)
    - Hospitals under N.H.I. (Box 30)
    - General (Box 30)
    - Accreditation of Hospitals (Box 30)
    - Affiliation of Hospitals (Box 30)
    - Administration (Box 30)
    - Ambulatory Services (Box 30)
    - Automatic Data Processing (Box 30)
    - Auxilary Specialists (Box 31)
    - Bingham Associates Consultation Program (Box 31)
    - Care for Chronically Ill (Box 31)
    - Community Needs, Hospitals as Related To (Box 31)
    - Contractual Physicians (Box 31)
    - Convalescent Care (Box 31)
    - Costs - Income and Expenditures, 1939-1949 (Box 31)
    - Diagnostic Services (Box 31)
    - Discrimination in Hospitals (Box 31)
    - Doctors' Offices in Hospitals (Box 31)
    - Emergency Units (Box 31)
    - Federal Hospitalization (Box 31)
    - Fund Raising (Box 31)
    - Government's Policies in Re: General Hospitals (Box 31)
    - Indigent Care (Box 31)
    - Labor Relations (Box 31)
    - Legislation - Crossfile under Legal Aspects (Box 31)
    - Malpractice Suits, Medical Professional Liability and Other Legal Issues (Box 31)
    - Medical Audit (Box 31)
    - Medical Staff and Employee Relations (Box 31)
    - Middle-Income Patients, Hospital Services for (Box 31)
    - Patient Relationships (Box 31)
    - Pharmacies in Hospitals (Box 31)
    - Philanthropy in Hospitals (Box 31)
    - Physician Relationships (Box 31)
    - Planning (Box 31)
    - Private Hospitals (Proprietary Hospitals) (Box 31)
    - Progressive Patient Care (Box 31)
    - Proto-type Studies (Box 31)
    - Psychiatry in Hospitals (Box 31)
    - Public Relations (Box 31)
    - Quality of Hospital Care (Box 31)
    - Rates (Box 31)
    - Regional Plans (Box 31)
    - Research (Box 31)
    - Rural Hospitals (Box 32)
    - Small Hospitals (Box 32)
    - "Socialized Medicine," Hospitals and (Box 32)
    - Staffing (Box 32)
    - Standards and Ethics (Box 32)
    - Teaching Hospitals (Box 32)
    - Trustees (Box 32)
    - Unions in Hospitals (Box 32)
    - Utilization of Health Facilities and Services (bibliography), 1960-1963 (Box 32)
    - Utilization of Hospitals (Box 32)
    - Voluntary Hospitals (Box 32)
  - News Letters and Hospital Councils and Organizations
    - ACHA News (Box 32)
    - Hospital Council of Metropolitan Boston (Box 32)
    - Hospital Council of Greater New York (Box 32)
    - Hospital Council of Philadelphia (Box 32)
    - Hospital Council of Western Philadelphia (Box 32)
    - Hospital Planning Council for Metropolitan Chicago (Box 32)
    - Medical Advance - Bellevue Medical Center (Box 32)
    - Organizations (Box 32)
  - Hospital Surveys and Studies
    - Hospital Surveys - National (Box 33)
    - Hospital Surveys - Regional and Local (Box 33)
    - Individual Hospitals (Box 33)
  - Hospitals - Pamphlets
    - Hospitals - Pamphlets (Box 33)
  - Hospital Administration
    - Training and Education for Hospital Administrators (Box 34)
  - Hospital Finances
    - General (Box 34)
    - Income from Tax Sources (Box 34)
  - Hospital Out-Patient Departments
    - Hospital Out-Patient Departments (Box 34-35)
  - Hospital Services and Functions Development
    - Hospital Services and Functions Development (Box 35)
  - Health Centers - Hospital Medical Centers
    - Health Centers - Hospital Medical Centers (Box 35)
  - Hospital Clinics
    - Hospital Clinics (Box 36)
  - American Hospital Association
    - General Reports and Pamphlets (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. - Current (Box 36)
    - A.H.A., 1947-1948 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A., 1937-1940 (Box 36)
    - Caldwell, Bert. W., M.D. (Box 36)
    - Hospital Service Plans - Reports by Director, 1939-1942 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Coordinating Committee, 1940-1942 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Coordinating Committee, July, 1938-December, 1939 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Coordinating Committee, through June, 1938 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Council on Community Relations, 1935-1937 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Council on Hospital Care Insurance (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Council on Professional Practice, 1938-1939 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Council on Public Education (MMD), 1940 (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Council on Public Education (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Institute for Hospital Administrators (Reports, Memos, Outlines, Lists) (Box 36)
    - Joint Committee of A.H.A. and American Public Welfare Association (Box 36)
    - A.H.A. Out-Patient Dept. Committee, 1929 and previous (Box 36)
  - Public Medical Care Programs
    - (Box 37)
  - Aged
    - Statistical Data and Facts on Aged and Aging (Box 37)
    - Philosophical and Sociological Problems of the Aged (other than health) (Box 37)
    - Needs of the Aged - Role of Voluntary Agencies (Box 37)
    - Health Problems of the Aged (Box 37)
    - Medical Care Needed and Obtained (Box 37)
    - Health/Hospitalization Insurance for the Aged (other than legislation for Medical Care for Aged under Social Security Mechanisms) (Box 37)
    - Homes for the Aged (see also Nursing Homes) (Box 37)
    - Proposals for Meeting Other Problems of the Aged (Box 37)
    - Proposals and Studies of Problems of Aged by States, Localities, and Regions (Box 37-38)
    - Legislative Hearings: National - Prints and Reports (Box 38)
  - Care of the Aged - OASI
    - Old Age and Survivors Insurance (Box 38)
    - Old Age, Public Assistance (Box 38)
    - Public Homes for the Aged (Box 38)
  - General Relief Data and Reports
    - National Committee on Health Care of the Aged (Box 38)
    - Financing Medical Care for the Aged (Symposium) (Box 38)
  - Public Medical Care - General
    - General (Box 38)
    - Admission Requirements (Box 38)
    - Eligibility (Box 38)
    - Family Nursing Needs (Box 38)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Administration (Box 38)
    - Financing (Box 38-)
    - Indigent Care (Box 38)
    - Maternity and Infant Care (Box 39)
    - Rehabilitation (Box 39)
    - Relationship to Voluntary Health and Welfare Agencies (Box 39)
    - Needs and Trends (see also Public Health), 1962-1966 (Box 39)
  - Public Medical Care - Reports and Studies by States and Localities
    - Aid to Dependent Children and Child Welfare Program (Box 39)
  - American Public Welfare Association
    - General Reports and Studies (Box 40)
    - A.P.W.A. - Individual Jackets for Years, 1936-1956 (Box 40)
    - A.P.W.A. - Medical Care Section: Individual Jackets for Years, 1944-1952 and Present (Box 41)
    - A.P.W.A. - M.M.D.'s 12/51 Meeting (Box 41)
    - A.P.W.A. - Hospital Study (Box 41)
  - Public Health
    - Bibliographies (Box 40)
    - Economics (Box 40)
    - Epidemiology (see also Environment and Health) (Box 40)
    - Health and Science (Box 40)
    - History (Box 40)
    - Legal Aspects (Box 40)
    - Needs, Policies, and Trends (Box 40)
    - Personnel (see also Health Manpower) (Box 40)
    - Programs of Activities (Box 40)
    - Research (Box 40)
    - Statistics (Box 40)
  - American Public Health Association
    - A.P.H.A. - Current and General (Box 40)
    - File Jackets for years, 1936-1943 (Box 41)
    - Communicable Disease Reports, 1929 (Box 41)
    - Dunker Study, 1931-1932 (Box 41)
    - Isolation Hospital Reports, 1931 (Box 41)
    - Twenty-five Questions Study, 1930-1931 (Box 41)
  - Public Health Services, H.E.W.
    - General Reports and Studies (Box 41)
    - Administration (Box 41)
    - Dental Programs (Box 41)
    - Drugs and Tranquilizers (Box 41)
    - Federal Grants-in-Aid (Box 41)
    - Food (Box 41)
    - Health Examinations (Box 41)
    - Health Information Series (Box 41)
    - Home Care Programs (see also Medical Care: Home Care Program) (Box 41)
    - Industrial Hygiene (Box 41)
    - Report on Smoking (see also Various Diseases...) (Box 41)
    - Statistics (Box 41)
    - Survey of Public Health Hospitals (Box 41)
  - Public Health - States
    - Pamphlets (Box 42)
    - Maryland Medical Care Program (Box 42)
  - Local Public Health Units
    - Local Public Health Units (Box 42)
  - Workmen's Compensation
    - General (Box 43)
    - Medical Care Aspects (Box 43)
    - Occupational Health Institute (Box 43)
    - State Laws (Box 43)
    - Rehabilitation (Box 43)
  - President's Commission on Health Needs of the Nation
    - Organization - Early Meeting (Box 52)
    - A.M.A. Controversy (Box 52)
    - President's Commission I: Findings and Recommendations, Volume I, 12/18/52, Jan., Feb., 1952 (Box 52)
    - President's Commission II, March-June, 1952 (Box 52)
    - Committee for the Nation's Health - Mimeographic Material on President's Commission's Hearings (Box 52)
    - President's Commission's Panel on Finance (MMD's Dept.), 10/7-8/52 (Box 52)
    - Articles and Releases (Box 52)
    - Press Comments, 1953 (Box 52)
    - Labor Press Comments (Box 52)
    - Transcripts of Commission's Meeting, 1/14-15/1952 (Box 52)
    - Clippings, Memos and Cartoons (Box 52)
    - Transcript of Commission's Meetings and Hearings (Box 52)
  - Salk Vaccine Debate -, 1955
    - Poliomyelitis Vaccine Hearings (Salk), 1955 (Box 52)
    - H.E.W. Releases (Box 52)
    - C.N.H. and MMD Comments Re: Salk (Box 52)
    - Bills - Salk Vaccine (Box 52)
    - Congressional Record Re: Salk Vaccine (Box 52)
    - Canada - Denmark: Salk Vaccine (Box 52)
    - A.M.A. Re: Salk Vaccine (Box 53)
    - Publications (Box 53)
    - Newspaper Clippings - Special (Box 53)
    - Newspaper Clippings - General (Box 53)
    - Organizations' Statements on Salk Vaccine (Box 53)
    - Collection of Newspaper Stories and Columns Re: Salk Vaccine and Individuals Involved (Box 53)
  - Veteran's Administration
    - VA Medical Care (Box 44)
  - War Stabilization Board Report on Health, Welfare and Pension Programs
    - War Stabilization Board Report on Health, Welfare and Pension Programs (Box 44)
  - "Medicare"
    - Medical Care for the Aged through Social Security (Box 44)
    - "Social Security Amendments of 1965" (Public Law 89-97) (Box 44)
- Legislation and Legal Aspects, Series 3
  Divided into seven sub-series.
  The National Health Insurance Legislation file contains original texts of bills, committee hearings, and basic data in the form of official publications and statements of organizations and individuals (clippings, correspondence, published releases, etc.). There are also folders of correspondence and other expressions of different and differing attitudes as evidenced by labor, "organized medicine," commercial and political organizations. The whole picture of a nation concernedis here -- and there are files of statements by personalities in all fields, newspaper and columnist's comments, articles from all kinds of magazines, along with radio and television publicity, and cartoons.
  Not only the early health insurance bills and actions sponsored by Flanders and Herter in 1949, the Humphrey Cooperative Health Act of 1949, and the Taft-Smith-Donnell action of 1946, 1947, and 1949 are here, but these records are accompanied by Dr. Davis' complete files of correspondence, clippings, confidential reports, and annotated copies of published items referring to these legislative movements. Most inclusive are the files on the Wagner-Murray-Dingell bills and their evolution from previous legislative proposals dating back more than 30 years.
  In addition to these specific files, there are materials on legislation since 1950, and pertinent publications, reports, correspondence, and ephemera relevant to legislation prior to 1950, public assistance and child welfare, mental health, and state legislation, including sickness and disability insurance programs to be paid for by the state.
  There are further materials on the legal aspects of hospitals, their medical staff relations, and licensing laws regarding hospitals and convalescent institutions. The file on legal suits and medical societies is especially fascinating, including as it does a unique scrapbook of newspaper clippings on "The A.M.A. Trial" of 1941, when the American Medical Association was indicted for alleged violation of the antitrust act. This, along with trial records of other legal actions affecting medical organizations, optical rebates, and so forth, give us substantial corps of reference materials not easy to come by and, in most cases -- particularly where Dr. Davis' correspondence or ephemera are added -- not to be duplicated in any other collection.
  - National Health Insurance Legislation
    - Legislative Proposals for Medical Care of Aged under Social Security Mechanism, 1957-1965 (Box 44-45)
    - Presidential Messages (Box 44)
    - Proposed National Health Programs (Box 44)
    - Health Insurance Bills (Box 44)
    - Wagner - Murray - Dingell Bills (Box 44-45)
    - Wagner Bills, 1939-1944 (Box 45)
  - National Health Legislation
    - Legislation, since 1950 (Box 45-46)
    - Legislation, prior to 1950 (Box 46)
  - Mental Health Legislation
    - Mental Health Legislation (Box 46)
  - Public Assistance and Child Welfare Legislation
    - Public Assistance and Child Welfare Legislation (Box 46)
  - State Legislation
    - State Legislation (Box 46)
    - State Cash Sickness and Disability Insurance (Box 46-47)
    - State Health Insurance Legislation Proposals (Box 47-48)
    - Miscellaneous State Health Legislation (Box 48)
    - US Possessions - Legislation (Box 48)
  - Legal Aspects of Hospitals
    - Hospitals and the Practice of Medicine (Box 48)
    - Licensing Laws (Box 48)
    - Hill-Burton Hospital Survey and Construction Draft (Box 48)
    - Legal Definition of Hospitals (Box 48)
    - Hospital Legislation in Canada - Report of Committee on Hospital Legislation (Box 48)
    - Medical Staff Relations (Box 48)
  - Legal Suits - Medical Societies
    - US Government Department of Justice (Box 48)
    - Legal Suits - General (Box 48)
    - Anti-Trust Act Suit: A.M.A. vs. S.S. (relates to Group Health Association of Washington, D.C.), 1938-1942 (Box 48)
    - The A.M.A. Trial (Box 49)
    - Elk City Community Hospital vs. County Medical Society (Box 49)
    - Complete Service Bureau vs.San Diego County Medical Society (Box 49)
    - Group Health Cooperative of Puget Sound (Box 49)
    - Optical Rebates (Box 49)
    - US vs. Oregon State Medical Society (Box 49)
- Organizations, Series 4
  Divided into eight subseries.
  Samples of special reports, annual reports, and letters to and from Dr. Davis concerning the work of various organizations are included in this part of the collection, which is grouped into the following sections: Professional Organizations, General Organizations, International Organizations, and Political Organizations.
  A large part of Dr. Davis' intrinsic interest in the dozens of organizations represented in this portion of the collection is more substantially supported by correspondence located by subject designation elsewhere in the files and, also, in the large part of the collection devoted to "Personalities." There is considerable material on rural or farm organizations and on a number of temporary groups.
  One of the chief values of the section devoted to organizations, however, is the inclusion of a good deal of material on groups now defunct or inactive, along with publications derived from them; also, many publications that are now unobtainable from organizations that are still existent are in the file drawers of the Academy.
  In addition to the miscellaneous organizations just commented on, also present is Dr. Davis' complete file of records, correspondence, interviews, confidential reports, etc., concerning the Committee for the Nation's Health, with articles promoted or arranged for by the committee in various publications, 1948 to 1956; there are also memoranda, minutes, and financial statements. Dr. Davis was, of course, chairman of the Executive Committee of the Committee for the Nation's Health. This is an absolutely unique and basic record of the work and administration of one of the most effective instruments for public education with regard to medical security ever to be active in this country. The work of the Committee for the Nation's Health, its internal administration and public programs, will serves as a model for many other social drives in the future. Likewise, the similar files of the Committee on the Research in Medical Economics (CRME) gives the Academy a corner on research in the field of medical economics. The unique, priceless archives of these two organizations will undoubtedly be the cornerstone of a research collection that will be of growing importance to all branches of the medical profession.
  The American Medical Association was, naturally, of prime interest to Dr. Davis and his colleagues in the various committees and groups with which he worked toward the goal of government-sponsored or government-supported health plans. The collection includes basic studies of the A.M.A., and its organization, with detailed publications, reports, correspondence, clippings, and private studies gathered from many sources. There are folders of correspondence with several individuals and officers of the A.M.A., with a good deal of supplementary material such as reports of the association's meetings, speeches made to them, etc. The A.M.A. files continue with medical societies (state and county) filled with correspondence as well as with clippings and other secondary source records of "position statements" made by auxiliary groups across the country during the years of the great debate on "socialized medicine."